Thank
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): you, Mr. Chairman. Thanks to the witnesses for being here. Ms. Gaines, I want to start with you. Thank you for your courage and being here today. Thank you for your courage and advocacy for women. You have been subjected to an unbelievable amount of abuse. You talk about intimidation, threats of violence. You have suffered it. I want to put up here a picture so everybody can see it. This was the welcome you were treated to at San Francisco State University just a couple of months ago when a
mob
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): Assembled where you were supposed to speak I believe for over three hours screamed threatened you Barricaded you in a room. Do I have
Man 2: that basically correct?
Speaker 3: Yes. I was held for ransom for three and a half hours By hundreds of
Speaker 4: these protesters as you see on the board They demanded that I had to pay them money if I wanted to make it home to see my family safe again the law enforcement in San Francisco
and
Speaker 4: I respect, and I think law enforcement is what's brave, not me, and I respect all law enforcement, but the law enforcement I was met with in San Francisco, in my opinion, failed miserably in effectively doing their job. They had mentioned that it was not ideal for
them to be
Speaker 4: seen as anything other than an ally to this community, and that was made very obvious in the treatment
and...
the
Speaker 4: effectiveness of removing me safely from that situation. Why
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): were you threatened and barricaded into a room and held for ransom for hours on end? I mean, what was it you were saying that was so terrible? I was
Speaker 4: invited to speak on my experience of my senior year in competing against a male. Nothing opinionated about what I shared. It was surely the exact lived experience of what me and my teammates and fellow competitors dealt with.
Speaker 4: And so I spoke, I, after my speech, there was of course a lot of protesters in the room, which I'm totally fine with people protesting, it's their right to protest, but what I'm not fine with is when it does turn violent in the way that it did. Because protesters afterwards, they rush into the room, they turn off the lights, they rush to the front,
Speaker 4: And myself and others were assaulted. And that's ultimately when I was held for hostage for three and a half hours.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): This is unbelievable, unbelievable. Thank you for your courage in the midst of that. Let's talk a little bit about the message that you were
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): sharing. And you started to talk about it in your opening statement.
Just tell
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): us about your experience because nobody can question your experience. I don't think anybody sitting at the table and certainly nobody at this podium has had the experience that you have had. You were talking
about
Just
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): the incredible surprise, shall I say, to put it gently, of finding
Man 2: a biological man, a six-foot-four biological man in your locker room and having to accept that without being asked about it, without being told about
Speaker 6: it even, what was that like for you? Tell us about that.
Speaker 4: Again, we only became aware we would be undressing next to a man when we had to see a man undressing while we were simultaneously undressing. And
so I
Speaker 4: immediately left the locker room and I went up to one of the officials on the pool deck and I said, "What are the guidelines to allow a man into our locker room? I know the guidelines for the competition, but what are the guidelines for the locker room?" And he so nonchalantly said back, "Oh, we actually got around this by making locker rooms unisex."
Speaker 4: And so I'm thinking to myself in these brief moments, first and foremost, you just admitted this as a male by acknowledging how you had to change your rules to make the locker rooms unisex.
You
Speaker 7 (higher-pitched voice): acknowledge that we do not share the same sex, first and foremost. Secondly, unisex, any man could have walked into our locker room, any coach, any official, any man who wanted to would have had full reigns to and bare minimum we weren't forewarned about
it.
And
Speaker 7 (higher-pitched voice): that's the traumatizing part. Of course, the experience in and of the locker room itself is
Speaker 4: traumatizing, but I think for me, it was so easy for them to dismiss our rights to privacy. Senator Durbin, in your opening statement, you had mentioned this rhetoric. You had mentioned
that
Speaker 4: What message does it send to trans
Speaker 7 (higher-pitched voice): individuals? And my combat to that is what message does this send to women, to young girls who are denied of these opportunities? So easily their rights to privacy and safety thrown out of the window to protect a small population, protect one group as long as they're happy. What about us? That is the overall
Speaker 8: general consensus of how we all felt in that locker room.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): - Why do you think it is that the NCAA
and so
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): many people in power seem intense in just erasing
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): your opinion, your views, the whole category of women? I noticed that recently you just posted this to social media about a message that Harvard was sending around, I think, to its swimmers, telling them don't talk about Leah Thomas, don't share your opinions. If you get contacted by a member of the media, then refer that to the university. Don't say anything, for heaven's sake. Tell us about this. I mean, this has been your experience over and over and over. You're told as a woman to shut up, don't say anything. What's that like?
That
Speaker 9: is continually happening, and if we do speak up, you're immediately labeled as some name. They will call you everything
Speaker 4: under the sun, whether it's transphobic, homophobic, racist, white supremacist, domestic terrorist. They will throw them all at you in hopes to deter you, in hopes to silence you. Leah Thomas' teammates, they were forced every single week to go to mandatory LGBTQ education meetings to learn about
Speaker 7 (higher-pitched voice): how just by being cisgender, they were oppressing Leah Thomas. They were told that they're not allowed to take a stance because their school has already taken their stance for them.
Speaker 7 (higher-pitched voice): them. They were told that you will never get a job, you will never get into grad school, you will lose your friends, you will lose your scholarship and playing time if you speak out. They told these girls that if you do speak out and any harm whatsoever comes towards Thomas's
Speaker 4: way, whether that's through social media, whether that's physical, mental, emotional harm, then you are solely responsible and you
Speaker 7 (higher-pitched voice): could be responsible for a potential death and you don't want that, do
you?
Of
Speaker 7 (higher-pitched voice): course not. Who would ever want to be responsible in a potential death? But that is the emotional blackmail that is plaguing this country, especially in universities.
Man 2: Last question. I'll ask this and then give you a chance to respond and I'm done with this, Mr. Chairman. Let me give you a chance to respond to something that Leah Thomas said recently, publicly. She said this publicly. They're using this quote now.
Man 2: They're using the guise of feminism, they meaning you, using the guise of feminism to sort of push transphobic beliefs, meaning you advocating for women, women's rights is actually just a cover for transphobia. Do you want to respond to that?
Feminism
Speaker 10: is not a fluid term. The original and the meaning of what it means to be a feminist
Speaker 4: is to uphold, respect, honor, embrace, and celebrate women on our own physical ceilings, our own uniqueness. That term has not changed. And what this really is is a male mansplaining what it is to be a feminist, which I honestly think is pretty ironic and it's something we've seen before.
Thank you, Senator
Speaker 11: Hawley.